Boker Tov בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. All right, we turn to a
new Mishnah משנה Mishnah today, Ayin Tet ע"ט, Ayin Tet, and we
move from a lot of these questions about Tevichah u-Mechira טביחה ומכירה,
Tevichah u-Mechira, which has been really occupying us, obviously in different ways.
Got into a fascinating whole Eidim Zomemim עדים זוממים Eidim Zomemim issue,
also just more narrow questions of what constitutes the Mechira מכירה. Mechira.
You have to sell the whole thing? If you hold back a
part of it? Shechita she-eina reuyah שחיטה שאינה ראויה. Shechita she-eina reuyah.
All these interesting things related to Tevichah u-Mechira טביחה ומכירה. Tevichah u-Mechira.
Now we get back to—it will be about Tevichah u-Mechira טביחה ומכירה,
Tevichah u-Mechira, but in some ways it will be much more basic
about the act of Geneivah גניבה Geneivah itself. So let's take a
look at the Mishnah משנה, Mishnah, Ayin Tet Amud Aleph ע"ט עמוד
א'. Ayin Tet Amud Aleph. Ganav bi-reshut ha-ba'alim גנב ברשות הבעלים: Ganav
bi-reshut ha-ba'alim: somebody stole it and he was still in the owner's
domain, ve-tavach u-machar chutz mei-reshutam וטבח ומכר חוץ מרשותם: ve-tavach u-machar chutz
mei-reshutam: but by the time he got around to slaughtering it, he
was out of their domain. Now I always wondered, you know, when
I was learning this in, you know, way back when,
you're mentioned like, how could somebody be in like my front yard
and stealing something from me? How does it constitute stealing from me?
You meant like, well, yes, but I'm just saying like what does
it mean to steal if you're standing there in my yard? So
if you imagine though, like I was thinking you know somebody that's
got like a, you know, like a farmer or whatever it is,
you know somebody's got acres and acres and acres of property, right?
So you could go ahead and you could like take something from
my, you know, from my sheep, from my pen, and go somewhere
else like, you know, a mile away or you know acre, you
know, like a long distance away and still be on my property.
For all I know you're camping out somewhere, you know, and you're
squatting on my property somewhere in the forest. Like if you imagine
somebody with wide property, you can steal something and still be on
the person's property, right? So it's still called stealing. Well, it's not.
That's the point. Meaning the point here is, the basic point of
this Mishnah משנה Mishnah is that to be a Ganav גנב, Ganav,
you have to actually take it out of the owner's Reshut רשות.
Reshut. And you might remember the Gemara גמרא Gemara earlier quoted a
Pasuk פסוק Pasuk of 'himatzei timatzei be-yado ha-geneivah המצא תמצא בידו הגניבה,
himatzei timatzei be-yado ha-geneivah, ein li ella yado gag chatzer u-kfifah minayin
talmud lomar himatzei timatzei' אין לי אלא ידו גג חצר וקפיפה מניין
תלמוד לומר המצא תמצא. ein li ella yado gag chatzer u-kfifah minayin
talmud lomar himatzei timatzei. So in order to be considered a Geneivah
גניבה, Geneivah, you have to take away from the owner and into
some sense of your own control. And that's really what this Mishnah
משנה Mishnah is getting about. If you just move it from one
place on the property to another, you haven't done yet an act
of Geneivah גניבה. Geneivah. Meaning it says Ganav גנב Ganav because in
some way you could say it looks like he stole it. You
have to even imagine a scenario where it practically it looks like
he stole it, but technically he hasn't because he hasn't taken it
out of their Reshut רשות. Reshut. Now the end of the Mishnah
משנה Mishnah is going to say—wait a minute, though—the end of the
Mishnah משנה Mishnah is going to talk about Hagbahah הגבהה, Hagbahah, right,
lifting it up. So although you don't get that sense in the
beginning of the Mishnah משנה, Mishnah, from the beginning of the Mishnah
משנה, Mishnah, the tendency you get is that he would have to
actually walk out of the property, right? That's bi-reshutam ברשותם. bi-reshutam. But
at the end of the Mishnah משנה Mishnah it's going to be
clear that lifting it up is taking it out of their Reshut
רשות. Reshut. You're taking possession. You know, your feet might be in
their Reshut רשות, Reshut, but you're taking it out of their Reshut
רשות. Reshut. So the case where it's 'you're in their Reshut רשות'
Reshut is you never lifted it up. And really what the implication
in the Mishnah משנה, Mishnah, although we'll discuss it Tosafot תוספות Tosafot
in a minute, the implication of the Mishnah משנה Mishnah is that
you have to do a normal Ma'aseh kinyan מעשה קניין, Ma'aseh kinyan,
the same type of an act that demonstrates ownership and taking away
from one person and taking into your possession. When you do an
act of taking a gift or buying an object or something of
that is the same act that defines somebody as having done an
act of Geneivah גניבה. Geneivah. Okay, so that would either be Hagbahah
הגבהה Hagbahah or Meshikhah משיכה Meshikhah or taking it into your Reshut
רשות. Reshut. Right, if you if something, if you put, if I'm
buying your cow from you and it walks into my property, being
in my property is a way. So I can either bring it
into my property, I could lift it up, or I could do
Meshikhah משיכה, Meshikhah, dragging it. But dragging it would not work while
it's in the seller's or original owner's domain. Meshikhah משיכה Meshikhah only
works if it's in some type of a neutral domain. Okay, so
as long as you remain on the property of the owner, there's
no Kinyan קניין Kinyan you can do except Hagbahah הגבהה. Hagbahah. So
what we have to assume is that the Mishnah משנה's Mishnah not
is talking that you haven't done Hagbahah הגבהה. Hagbahah. So wherever you
are on that domain, if you haven't done Hagbahah הגבהה, Hagbahah, you
haven't really halachically stolen. I don't have to lift it up, it
has to be lifted, right? Like let's say I drive my pickup
truck... All right, let's not talk about the Gemara גמרא Gemara about
the elephant, I mean fine. That was an exception. Okay, whether you
could do something and throw some peanut up, but let's assume you
have to pick it up. Okay, so I understand contextualize. I understand.
I take my my pickup truck, whatever it is, there's a ramp,
it walks onto the, you know... Yeah, so that was a Gemara
גמרא Gemara discussed in Kiddushin קידושין Kiddushin maybe. Okay, but that's not
the standard case, maybe. But by the way, if we're talking about
a Shor שור, Shor, an ox, so then you understand why Hagbahah
הגבהה Hagbahah is not even being considered reasonably. I mean Michael is
correct, it is possible maybe that you can make an animal jump
up or get off the air or something like that,
but nevertheless the standard, certainly by a sheep, Hagbahah הגבהה Hagbahah would
be natural, but by an ox not. So as long as you're
in the owner's domain and you haven't done Hagbahah הגבהה, Hagbahah, you
haven't done an act of Geneivah גניבה. Geneivah. That's the basic principle
of this Mishnah משנה. Mishnah. Okay, so let's take a look. Ganav
bi-reshut ha-ba'alim גנב ברשות הבעלים: Ganav bi-reshut ha-ba'alim: you burgled it and
you're still in their domain, ve-tavach u-machar chutz mei-reshutam וטבח ומכר חוץ
מרשותם: ve-tavach u-machar chutz mei-reshutam: but by the time it came to
slaughtering or selling, you were out of their domain. Okay. O she-ganav
chutz mei-reshutam או שגנב חוץ מרשותם. o she-ganav chutz mei-reshutam. or you
took it out of their domain, or maybe just took possession of
it while it was wandering in some neutral zone, maybe did a
משיכה, meshichah, וטבח ומכר ברשותם, vetavach umachar birshutam, and then for some
reason you wandered back into their domain and you sold it. Right
again, you could imagine somebody's on some part of my property, my
huge estate, somebody is on it and he is and he's selling
somebody else my sheep. And this person, you know, it's like the
Brooklyn Bridge story, right? I'll sell you these sheep, you know. Okay,
they're not my sheep but the other person doesn't know that. The
other person sees me in this property walking around with these sheep.
He thinks I'm the owner. So I'm in the owner's property and
I'm selling his sheep, okay? But I've already stolen them because I
did take it חוץ מרשותם chutz mershutam at one stage. Now the
sale, the transaction is happening on their property. Okay. In all those
cases, או שגנב וטבח ומכר חוץ מרשותם, o sheganav vetavach umachar chutz
mershutam, that's the obvious case. I both stole it and sold it
out of their property.
תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. tashlumei arbaah vachamishah. You pay four and five. אבל
גנב וטבח ומכר ברשותם, aval ganav vetavach umachar birshutam, if I never
actually took it out of their property in any stage, פטור, patur,
I'm exempt because I never did an act of גניבה gneivah ארבעה
וחמישה arbaa vachamisha or even כפל. kefel. Well, if I שחט-ed shachat
it, I'm a מזיק. mazik. But if I didn't שחט, shachat, then
I'm חייב chayav nothing. I didn't even do an act of גניבה,
gneivah, right? Now by the way, רש"י Rashi says, there's an interesting
question about a גרסא girsa in רש"י, Rashi, because רש"י Rashi says,
well actually that's a later רש"י. Rashi. What? What don't you understand?
I moved around your sheep within your domain and then I sold
it to somebody and I walked away. Right. And what did I
do? I don't have to pay you for the value of the
sheep? What did I do to you? What did I do? I
killed your sheep! I no, killed I said you would, you're a
מזיק. mazik. וגנב וטבח ומכר. veganav vetavach umachar. Okay fine. So that
case you would. But let's say it was מכר. machar. Whatever as
a גנב, ganav, you're פטור. patur. If you were טבח, tavach, fine,
you're a מזיק. mazik. If I was מכר, machar, if I went
ahead and I stole your property that I kept on your domain
and I sold it here to Eli and he walked away with
it thinking it was his and I just walked away with the
whole and I just left. It means I left for him, is
that it? You have to go after him. I don't have to
go after him. I was just a גרמא, grama, I was just
a troublemaker. What no, I'm not. Why am I חייב chayav a
תרעומת? taromet? What no, it means if I did it, if I
sold it to him. Let's say it's your sheep and I went
and sold to him all of a sudden your property. What did
I do? I don't want him to sell it. Of course, I'm
not saying he's a good guy. Who do I have to go
after him or after go after me? I have to go after
him. If you sold it whatever, he's got my sheep. You were
a troublemaker but you were a גרמא, grama, right? What did you
do? So I get to keep the money then? What? And then
he does the same with me, is that it? No, I'm actually
exaggerating a little bit because
because we're going to see at the end of the משנה, mishnah,
a question how to read the end of the משנה. mishnah. But
there might be a way in which if you cause him to
take it thinking it's yours, that there is a type of a
שליח לדבר עבירה shliach lidvar aveirah and that's as if you took
it away from me, okay? And that at least you would be
have to pay me the קרן. keren. That's possible. Okay, we'll see
about that at the end of the משנה. mishnah. But right now
what you're saying is I go after him and then he can
go after me to get the money back? Yeah. Well no. You
were just oh, to get your money back, yeah, to get his
money back. But if you gave it to them as a מתנה.
matanah. No, but I just sold it to him. Fine, yes. What
about this גנב וטבח ומכר מחוץ? ganav vetavach umachar michutz? How how
does that work? Right. So that's a good question. So look at
רש"י Rashi because what what does it mean טבח ומכר חוץ מרשותם?
tavach umachar chutz mershutam? Means that I basically I took the sheep,
I moved it to another place on the property and then it
that wasn't yet a מעשה גניבה, maaseh gneivah, then it followed me
outside of the property and I sold it there. So where exactly
did I do my מעשה גניבה? maaseh gneivah? On the property wasn't
a מעשה גניבה. maaseh gneivah. It so presumably
so presumably it means so look at רש"י. Rashi. That's a good
question that you asked that. רש"י Rashi says וטבח ומכר חוץ מרשותו,
vetavach umachar chutz mershuto, the first
רש"י. Rashi. He says כשהוציאו מרשות נעשה עליו גנב וקנאו. keshehotzio mershut
naaseh alav ganav veknao. So רש"י Rashi says it doesn't literally mean
that no, that only the מכירה mechira happened out of the רשות.
reshut. It means first I stole it and then right, and then
when it it came time to sell it, I took it out
of the רשות reshut and I sold it. So that moment of
taking it out of the רשות, reshut, that was being a גנב,
ganav, right? But if literally, if literally I did I just moved
it in the רשות reshut and it followed me out and then
I sold it without me ever having done a מעשה קניין maaseh
kinyan then I would not be חייב. chayav. So it's a funny
because the משנה mishnah is like imprecise, you know. Basically what the
משנה mishnah saying is at one stage you gotta do a מעשה
קניין. maaseh kinyan. You gotta do a הגבהה hagbah or you gotta
take it out of the רשות הבעלים. reshut habaalim. And if you
haven't, you're not a גנב. ganav. Okay? So let's keep on reading.
Okay. Now. אבל גנב וטבח ומכר ברשות aval ganav vetavach umachar birshut
oh I did I did that. היה מושכו ויוצא, haya moshcho veyotze,
you were dragging it as your משיכה meshichah and bringing it out
of the property ומת umet and the animal died ברשות הבעלים birshut
habaalim פטור. patur.
If it died right before crossing the the, you know, the property
line, you're exempt. You have not been a גנב. ganav. Why? If
משיכה meshichah is a way of being doing קניין. kinyan. Not in
רשות הבעלים. reshut habaalim. משיכה meshichah only works out of the רשות
הבעלים. reshut habaalim. So you never crossed that boundary line. The only
thing that works in רשות הבעלים reshut habaalim is הגבהה, hagbah, which
is the next line of the
משנה. mishnah. Okay, הגביהו higbiho או הוציאו מרשות הבעלים o hotzio mershut
habaalim ומת umet and he dies. חייב. chayav. Okay, so this really
this line of the משנה mishnah is much clearer than the first
part of the משנה. mishnah. You have to do a הגבהה hagbaha
if you're in רשות הרבים reshus harabbim or משיכה meshicha out of
רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. If you haven't done that, you're not a
גנב ganav and you're not going to pay כפל, kefel, you're not
going to pay ארבעה וחמישה, arba'ah v'chamishah, etc. Okay, you just moved
around somebody's object, you're not a גנב. ganav. Now, very important תוספות
tosafot of הוציאו מרשות הרבים. hotziu me-reshus harabbim. Look at this תוספות.
tosafot. We're going to interrupt the משנה mishnah for a minute. Look
at this תוספות. tosafot. בריש אלו נערות, be-reish elo naaros, פליגי רב
אחא ורבינא. pligi Rav Acha v'Ravina. חד אמר שהוציאו לסימטא, chad amar
she-hotziu l'simta,
when you took it out of the owner's domain, you brought it
into some side street, okay, וחד אמר אבל רשות הרבים לא קני,
v'chad amar aval reshus harabbim lo kani,
but if you brought it from the owner's domain straight into the
public domain, that's not a קנין kinyan of משיכה, meshicha, because משיכה
meshicha needs to be in some domain that you can have some,
you, the new owner, the גנב ganav or whoever, needs some degree
of control over it. It has to be a pseudo-your domain. So
if it's in a side street, an alley, it's like, okay, nobody
is here, it's like I'm controlling this space. But משיכה meshicha in
רשות הרבים reshus harabbim doesn't work. So it's only when you dragged
it out of the owner's domain into an alley that it works.
Okay, אבל רשות הרבים לא קני, aval reshus harabbim lo kani, ודייק
מסיפא, v'dayek mi-seifa, הוציאו דומיא דהגביה, hotziu dumya d'hagbi'ah, דאתו לרשותו, de-asu
l'reshuso,
the same way הגבהה hagbaha is like you fully take control over
it, the משיכה meshicha is in a way in which you have
some control over it, into an alley. ואידך אמר, v'idach amar, and
the other one says, אפילו הוציאו לרשות הרבים קני. afilu hotziu l'reshus
harabbim kani. No, even if you just take it into the public
domain, ודייק מרישא, v'dayek mi-reisha, דהיה ברשות הבעלים פטור, d'haya be-reshus ha-be'alim
patur, because it emphasizes if it died before it left the domain
you're exempt. It sounds as soon as it leaves the domain, even
if it's into a public space, just taking it out of the
domain suffices, פטור, patur, החוץ לרשות חייב אפילו הוציאו לרשות הרבים. ha-chutz
l'reshus chayav afilu hotziu l'reshus harabbim.
Now, stop for a moment. So תוספות tosafot said a great question.
Is it enough to take it out of the owner's domain, or
do you have to take it into some space, an alley, that
you're taking it into your control? Now, it seems like this is
a perfect question of whether a גנב ganav is the same, we
said it's a מעשה קנין ma'aseh kinyan like taking possession of any
object. But is that really true? Right? For me to take possession
through משיכה, meshicha, it's presumably, it's universally assumed, that I have to
do a משיכה meshicha in an alley. I can't do משיכה meshicha
in רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. I need to have control, I need
to demonstrate that I'm taking possession. But here becomes an interesting question.
Maybe for a גנב ganav you don't need to be the one
that takes possession, you just need to be the one to take
it away from the owner. From the owner's perspective, he doesn't care
how much you're taking it to yourself, he cares that you're taking
it away from him. Okay, so maybe that's the, this is the
perfect test case. You took it out of his control, out of
his רשות, reshus, but you didn't take possession of it because it
wasn't in a סימטא. simta. Are you a גנב ganav or not?
And it seems like that is a debate of the אמוראים. amora'im.
What a great conceptual question, and therefore it's maybe not the exact
same as a normal מעשה קנין. ma'aseh kinyan. Okay, it's similar enough
because half of a מעשה קנין ma'aseh kinyan is taking it away
from the owner. But does it have to be similar fully, does
it have to also be about taking it under your control? Now
that I would, you would love to say, I would love to
say, תוספות tosafot denies that we should be making a distinction between
a גנב ganav and a normal purchaser. And he says if they're
debating that, they would be having the same debate about a normal
קנין kinyan about משיכה meshicha in general. That's the next line of
תוספות, tosafot, which is, which is a little deflating. Because he says
ונראה דפליגי אביי ורבא דאמרי בפרק המוכר את הספינה משיכה קונה בסימטא
ולא ברשות הרבים. v'nireh d'pligi Abaye v'Rava d'amri be-perek ha-mocher es ha-sefinah
meshicha koneh be-simta v'lo be-reshus harabbim. In בבא בתרא, Bava Basra, it
seems like Abaye and Rava and presumably everybody agrees משיכה meshicha only
works in an alley. He says it looks like it argues on
that, ואין נראה לחלק כלל בין קניית גנב שאינו אלא להתחייב באונסין
ולשאר קניות. v'ein nireh l'chalek klal bein kniyas ganav she-eino ela l'hischayev
be-onsin ul'shear kniyos. And it doesn't make any sense to say that
a גנב ganav should be defined differently than normal taking of possession.
Why? Because of the דרשה. drashah. I mean,
we made the דרשה drashah earlier. לגבי גנב אין לי אלא ידו
גגו חצירו וקפיצו מנין? legabei ganav ein li ela yado gago chatziro
v'kafiso minayin? So the דרשה drashah for a גנב ganav was המצא
תמצא בידו, himatze simatze be-yado, right?
So and your possession, it does emphasize the גנב's ganav possession, right?
And it says, you know, and his roof and his yard, it
emphasizes the possession of the גנב. ganav. משמע דלא מחייב אלא במקום
שראוי לקנות. mashma d'lo mechayev ela be-makom she-ra'uy liknos. It sounds like
it has to be a place where he can take possession. So
תוספות tosafot claims that really, whatever debate it is, it's just a
general debate about משיכה. meshicha. But it is more interesting to think
that no, maybe there actually is an opinion that says that for
a גנב ganav to be חייב, chayav, he doesn't have to be
able to do an act that shows he's taking possession of it,
it's enough to do an act that's taking it away from the
owner. By the way, it could be that there's a difference between
קרן keren and כפל. kefel. Okay, the פסוק pasuk of המצא תמצא
בידו הגניבה משור עד חמור עד שה חיים שנים ישלם himatze simatze
be-yado ha-gneiva mishor ad chamor ad seh chayim shnayim yeshaleim is about
כפל. kefel. Maybe the fine of כפל kefel is only when he
took He doesn't have to be able to do an act that
shows he's taking possession of it. It's enough to do an act
of taking it away from the owner. By the way, it could
be that there's a difference between קרן Keren and כפל. Kefel. Okay,
the פסוק Pasuk of אם המצא תמצא בידו הגנבה משור עד חמור
עד שה חיים שנים ישלם Im Himatze Timatze BeYado HaGneva MiShor Ad
Chamor Ad Seh Chayim Shnayim Yeshalem is about כפל. Kefel. Maybe the
fine of כפל Kefel is only when he took it to himself,
but the קרן Keren is about taking it away from the owner.
Right? So maybe if you bring it into רשות הרבים, Reshus HaRabim,
you're חייב Chayav in the principal. Once you bring it into your
own domain, that maybe is when you're חייב Chayav in כפל. Kefel.
Okay, so very interesting question here of what this משנה Mishna is
about, what is the act, the moment which a גנב Ganav has
done the act of גניבה. Gneivah. And you know, some key points
are missing from this משנה. Mishna. Clear from the end that we'd
seem to be talking about normal קניינים, Kinyanim, but תוספות Tosafot raises
the important question of is it just taking it away from the
owner or even taking possession yourself? Yes, Michael. So two points. You
know, one is, I mean, I can certainly see the moment you
take it out of the בית, Bayis, I thought that, you know,
when you take it out of, it's וגונב מבית האיש, Vegunav MiBeis
HaIsh, so you take it out of בית האיש, Beis HaIsh, then
you're a גנב. Ganav. So forget about, you know, having to bring
it into the place like, I was thinking רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim
would work. I
understand, but that's the, but the פסוק Pasuk is בידו, BeYado, גונב
מבית האיש אם המצא תמצא בידו ישלם שנים. Gunav MiBeis HaIsh Im
Himatze Timatze BeYado Yeshalem Shnayim. I understand. But let me just understand
kind of a broader point. So what you're saying is, let's say
you're at a pet shop, right? I go, and I buy a
dog, right? And then, you know, you're on right on whatever, wherever
it is, I'm trying to, a, right, so there's no, רשות הרבים
Reshus HaRabim there, you're in Times Square. Then you go take it
onto the subway, you know, and like, I could be on a,
on an hour trip, and then it dies. I can say, cancel
because I never actually was. And you've never done הגבהה? Hagbah? Yeah,
yes, if you've never done הגבהה Hagbah and you've never been in
any space that's not like a major public space. I mean, you're
right then, yeah, technically you could be, you are in, you are
in, you've never been in a space that, you know,
a private,
whatever, right. You've never been in a semi-private or private space. You've
only been in a public space, right, then yeah, you've never really
taken possession. I know, it's, I hear your point, it's funny, you
can be like very, very far away and not have taken, yeah.
Okay, I mean, you still, fine, yes. Okay, so now the משנה
Mishna continues. And that means you can't sell something in a private,
in a public space basically unless somebody lifts it. Well, you can
do הגבהה, Hagbah, you might be able to do קניין חליפין, Kinyan
Chalipin, like if, if it's something that could be put into some
vessel, in a knapsack or something like that.
But, yeah, I mean, you're right. Like in a normal store, I
mean, it's a good point that you're asking me. Like in a
normal store, you're right, I mean, I, I don't normally think about
selling dogs or refrigerators, you know, right? In a normal store, you
wouldn't be חייב Chayav until,
but yeah, you have to either lift it up or put it
into your, into your bag or something of that nature, right. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, where were we now? נתנו, Nasno, now here the next line
of the משנה Mishna is a big question about who are we
talking about. I'm go, I'm gonna first read it the way that
רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot reject, because to get it out of
the way. Okay, they read that the, one way to read this
משנה Mishna is that since we're talking about the act of a
קניין Kinyan of a גנב, Ganav, we're going to talk about in
general that an act of a קניין Kinyan is necessary to define
when some, you know, you know, like when something has left your
רשות. Reshus. So here would be another case, not about a גנב.
Ganav. I just am a normal homeowner
and I gave my sheep because my son is the firstborn, so
I gave my sheep as a כהן Kohen for the five סלעים
Sela'im that I owed the כהן Kohen for פדיון הבן. Pidyon HaBen.
Okay, or לבעל חוב, LeBa'al Chov, or I paid it to Michael
who I owed a hundred dollars to, I gave him my sheep.
Or I gave it לשומר חינם לשואל לנושא שכר ולשוכר. LeShomer Chinam
LeSho'el LeNosei Sachar UleSocher. I gave it to some שומר Shomer to
watch it for me, or to somebody who is renting it for
me. And you, Michael, who was the שומר Shomer or the כהן
Kohen or the guy who I owed money to, ומשכו, Umeshacho, you
were taking it out of my domain. ומת, Umes, and it died
before it left my domain. Right? So it'd be, meaning it's a
similar scenario, not about a גנב. Ganav. Right? At, have I actually
paid off my debt? Have I actually paid the money for my
פדיון הבן? Pidyon HaBen? Are you חייב Chayav as a שומר? Shomer?
You took it, you were dragging it away, but you didn't yet
cross the property line. So it's the same הלכה. Halakha. Okay, but
it's משיכה, Meshichah, it's not הגבהה. Hagbah. Okay, ומת ברשות בעלים פטור.
Umes BiReshus Ba'alim Patur.
So if it died while it's still in my, while it's still
in my domain, at least in the שומר Shomer case, you, Michael,
are פטור Patur because you haven't yet taken possession of it. Okay,
in the בעל חוב Ba'al Chov case, this is one of the
reasons רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot reject it, because in the בעל
חוב Ba'al Chov case, the word פטור Patur doesn't make sense. The
really is I still o, you know,
I still owe you the money, right? You have, I haven't paid
my debt yet, and I still owe you the money. In the
פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen case, I still have to do פדיון הבן.
Pidyon HaBen. Okay, but the, so one, but if in the שומר
Shomer case, you're פטור, Patur, you haven't taken possession yet. הגביהו או
שהוציאו מרשות בעלים, Higbi'o O SheHotzi'o MiReshus Ba'alim, if, however, Michael lifted
it up or he actually walked it out of my רשות, Reshus,
ומת חייב, Umes Chayav, and he's a שומר Shomer and then it
dies, then he is חייב. Chayav. So that's saying we're not even
talking about a גנב, Ganav, just in general, a similar scenario. The
key moment of, of transition, you know, when it switches from me
to belong to the other person as a payment of a debt
or as a שומר, Shomer, whatever, is either משיכה Meshichah out of
my רשות Reshus or הגבהה. Hagbah. Now the reason רש"י Rashi and
תוספות Tosafot don't like... is not just because it switches from talking
about a גנב, ganav, that wouldn't be a big deal, but is
that number one as we said, the word פטור patur isn't really
relevant to the case of בעל חוב ba'al chov and בכור בנו.
bechor beno. It's only relevant to the case of שומר. shomer. No,
פטור patur meaning like I've fulfilled my obligation not to have to
repay you again. But that's the opposite. If you're taking it out
and it died beforehand, I'm, you know, I still owe you the
money. I'm not פטור, patur, I'm still חייב. chayav. Think about it,
it's the opposite. Okay, so number one is the word doesn't work.
Now maybe you could say well we're talking about the last case
of שומר, shomer, we're borrowing the phrase from the previous but it's
not exactly the right phrase to be using by the payment of
a debt. But the other problem is also that what do you
call it, that שומרים shomrim if the animal just died, anybody other
than a שואל shoel would be exempt. So the whole idea that
we're talking about it died and whether the שומר shomer is חייב
chayav or not is not a normal scenario. Like we'd have to
be talking about it died through negligence which is not פשט. pshat.
So they put that read aside and therefore they read it that
we're still talking about the גנב. ganav. So let's now read it
again talking about the גנב. ganav. Okay? I went ahead and I
stole a sheep on Michael's property. Okay like I said I'm somewhere
a mile away in his huge estate and I'm at some edge
of his property and I'm doing a transaction with a כהן Kohen
and I say oh you know I'm camping out in a forest
in his estate he doesn't even know and I set up my
whole shop there whatever. Okay and I stole his sheep and then
I invite a כהן Kohen over because I just had a baby
boy מזל טוב mazal tov I'm going to do a פדיון הבן.
pidyon haben. And therefore I the גנב ganav who has yet to
do a מעשה קנין ma'aseh kinyan on this sheep, נתנו לבכור בנו
nesano livochor beno I gave it to this כהן Kohen for my
son's פדיון הבן pidyon haben on Michael's property. או לבעל חובו o
liva'al chovo or
Eli there I owed him a hundred dollars so I gave him
this sheep I was on Michael's property I gave him this sheep
because I haven't done הגבהה hagbaha or anything on it. או לשומר
חנם ולשואל נושא שכר והשוכר o lishomer chinam ulishoel noseh sachar vehasocher
or I gave it to David here to be my שומר shomer
on it or something. Now the question is not whether I've paid
my debt to Eli or done my פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. The
question is now, and this gets back to the point you raised
earlier Michael, you are now taking it thinking it's yours. You're taking
it in all innocence and you're doing a מעשה קנין ma'aseh kinyan
on it and you're going to walk off the property with it.
The moment you lift it up or walk off the property, you
become essentially my שליח shaliach and you have now done the מעשה
גנבה ma'aseh gneivah for me. And when you lift it up thinking
it's yours because I paid my debt or thinking you're taking possession
of it even just as a שומר shomer but you're doing some
act of taking possession of it you know on my behalf as
long as you're oblivious to the fact otherwise אין שליח לדבר עבירה
ein shaliach lidvar aveirah we'll get to that in a minute. But
you're oblivious in all your innocence you're thinking it and therefore in
that case it's like I did the מעשה גנבה ma'aseh gneivah and
I would be חייב. chayav. And that's what the end of the
משנה mishnah says, at least for אונסים. onessim. היה מושכו ומת ברשות
הבעלים פטור. hayah moshcho umes bireshus habaalim patur. Wait
so you, I the גנב ganav am פטור, patur, not you. Eli
there is taking it out, here's my כהן Kohen for פדיון הבן.
pidyon haben. He's effectively being my unwittingly being my שליח shaliach to
the גנבה, gneivah, he's taking possession of it. If he crosses that
property line and the animal dies, as if he crosses that property
line then I become a גנב ganav and anything and I have
to pay for the animal. If he didn't cross the property line
and the animal dies, I'm not yet a גנב. ganav. It's all
a question whether I'm a גנב. ganav. If you the שומר shomer
or you the creditor or you the כהן Kohen has done a
מעשה קנין ma'aseh kinyan on it, you've walked off the property line,
then I'm the גנב ganav and I become חייב. chayav. If you
haven't, then I am פטור. patur. Let me finish reading the משנה.
mishnah. Okay so in that case היה מושכו ומת ברשות הבעלים פטור,
hayah moshcho umes bireshus habaalim patur, then I the גנב ganav am
פטור. patur. הגביהו או שהוציאו מרשות הבעלים higbiho o shehotzio mereshus habaalim
once this guy took it out of רשות הבעלים reshus habaalim they
did the גנבה gneivah for me ומת חייב. umes chayav. Now what
I don't know from this, first of all that's a huge חדוש
chiddush that יש שליח לדבר עבירה. yesh shaliach lidvar aveirah. What I
don't know is would I also be חייב chayav in כפל? kefel?
אי שליח ay shaliach I don't know. Well that's exactly it. So
let's look first at, so at תוספות. Tosfos. So תוספות Tosfos says,
if תוספות Tosfos נתנו לבכור בנו nesano livochor beno if you go
like five lines in middle of the line ואם תאמר. veim tomar.
Do you see that like smack in the middle of the line
there? ואם תאמר ואמאי מחייב במשיכה. veim tomar veamai mechayev bimeshicha. והא
אין שליח לדבר עבירה veha ein shaliach lidvar aveirah you can't be
my שליח. shaliach. ויש
לומר
דהנהו לא ידעי דאתי לידיה באיסורא veyesh lomar dehaneihu lo yadai deasei
liyadei beissura you don't know you're doing anything wrong, you think you
know you're it's in all innocence אלא דבורים שהיה שלו ela devarim
shehayah shelo you think it belongs to the גנב. ganav. Now that
answer is the reason of אין שליח לדבר עבירה. ein shaliach lidvar
aveirah. Now remember אין שליח לדבר עבירה ein shaliach lidvar aveirah is
not a normal שליחות. shlichus. Normal שליחות shlichus is I'm authorized to
do something and I'm transferring that authority to you. שליח לדבר עבירה
shaliach lidvar aveirah would mean, the important thing to appreciate as we
continue to read תוספות, Tosfos, it's it's more sort of like, right,
remember in the גמרא Gemara I don't know if you remember it
in קידושין Kiddushin the גמרא Gemara spoke about if somebody hires somebody
to kill someone, right, it's a you know according to שמאי Shammai
there's a שליח לדבר עבירה shaliach lidvar aveirah and שמאי Shammai said
it was really like דינא רבא ודינא זוטא dina raba vedina zuta
he could be, either the murderer is still the murderer I take
the opposite in American law it's the person... that like hires the
murderer that's somehow seen as worse, right? Isn't that true? Like is
it, I think if you contract a murder. Anyway, whatever. Okay, but
the murderer is still the primary murderer. But the guy who contracted
him, he's like, he brought about the murder. So the idea of
שליח לדבר עבירה shliach lidvar aveira in a way is, not like
you're authorized to do this act of גניבה gneiva on my behalf.
It's more like a גרמא. grama. I managed to do the גניבה
gneiva through using you. You became my כלי kli to do the
גניבה. gneiva. Okay? So that's how he says it works when you're
unwitting. If you know what you're doing, if you know you shouldn't
be doing it, you can't say I'm using you. You should be
making your own choices. But if you're, if you're oblivious and you're
doing something that is completely natural that anybody would do, take payment
of a debt, right? You know, that of course you would do
it. So then you are in that case, you are a tool
in my hand. And I am stealing it through you because you
are unwitting. Okay? So that's what he says. ובין ללישנא דמפרש בפרק
קמא דבבא מציעא, u-vein le-lishna de-mefaresh be-perek kama de-Bava Metzia, טעמא דאין
שליח לדבר עבירה, ta'ama de-ein shliach lidvar aveira, why is there no
שליח? shliach? משום דשליח בר חיובא הוא, mishum de-shliach bar hiyuva hu,
you are an obligated person, you're a person who has, I mean,
you know, responsibilities and you know, the מצוות mitzvos obligations, דברי הרב
ודברי התלמיד דברי מי שומעין, divrei ha-rav ve-divrei ha-talmid divrei mi shomin,
and you should know not to listen to me, you should listen
to God. So here you don't know to listen to God because
you don't know you're doing anything wrong. Okay, ובין ללישנא דאי בעי
עביד ואי בעי לא עביד, u-vein le-lishna de-i ba'ei avid ve-i ba'ei
lo avid, the other one which says you can choose to do
it or not and therefore when I have you do it, it's
like, bah, I didn't know he was going to take it, he
might have chosen not to do it, you can't call me a
גנב. ganav. So what if I gave it to this guy? Who
said he was going to listen to me? But that's not true,
of course he was going to listen to you, you're paying off
a debt, why shouldn't he listen to you?
אין שייך לכאן, Ein shayach le-chan, משום דהתם אינו יודע שהשליח יעבור.
mishum de-hasam eino yodeia she-ha-shliach ya'avor. There you can say, yeah, I
didn't know he would listen to me, don't tell me I stole
it, he stole it, I didn't know he was going to listen
to me. אבל כאן יודע הוא שיקח מאחר דחסר בשלו הוא. Aval
kan yodeia hu she-yikach me-acher de-chaser bi-shelo hu. Of course he's going
to do it. Okay? So here, if somebody is, it's really a
fascinating idea of שליח לדבר עבירה. shliach lidvar aveira. Now again, it
wouldn't apply like if I get you to eat חזיר chazir thinking
that it's kosher, oh now I ate חזיר. chazir. That's also anyway
for things that are about about getting הנאה, hana'ah, things like food,
obviously it only relates to the person who directly experiences the הנאה.
hana'ah. But at least within the realm of a type of a,
one would wonder if this would apply to like other בין אדם
למקום bein adam la-makom type of cases. I'd have to think about
what a scenario would be about that.
What? Stolen art. Stolen art.
Yeah, that's בין אדם למקום, bein adam la-makom, but I'm thinking let's
say בין אדם לחברו. bein adam le-chaveiro. Let's do another בין אדם
למקום. bein adam la-makom. Let's say, I don't know, I took a
boy to the barber, Michael here's a barber, and I took a
boy to him and I said, oh yes, I'm I'm I'm a
babysitter for this gentile boy and he wants his haircut or whatever.
And for whatever reason Michael, I mean you could say he should
have had been suspicious about it, but whatever, let's just imagine this
for a moment. Let's say he was completely oblivious, he had total
right because he knew in general that I was a babysitter for
this gentile family. So of course he had total right to assume
that as whatever the reason was. Okay? And then he cuts a
and he goes ahead and he cuts off the פאות, peyos, okay?
So or let's use it for a בר מצווה. bar mitzvah. Okay?
So would you say, oh, so now I'm חייב chayav for for
cutting off the פאות? peyos? Because Michael of course was going to
listen to me, right? Or does this only true even when you
say something like this in something that's basically בין אדם לחברו. bein
adam le-chaveiro. בין אדם לחברו Bein adam le-chaveiro really focuses on the
impact of the act, right? Not so much on like the formal,
like it's not like a מעשה עבירה ma'aseh aveira that's a ritual
thing which has a very formal act. Here it's the impact. So
since I brought about that this object was taken away, then I
am seen as the גנב. ganav. So it's an interesting idea that
יש שליח לדבר עבירה yesh shliach lidvar aveira in a case when
the person the שליח shliach is unwitting, but I think it's an
interesting question whether you would apply it also to like ritual עבירות
aveiros or just sort of like, you know, ethical עבירות aveiros as
it were. Okay? But that's the case. He does it unwitting, he
does it, it's like I stole it from Michael now when Eli
takes it off the property and I'm חייב. chayav. And the question
I'm left asking is, am I חייב chayav just in the קרן,
keren, which is the case of the משנה, mishna, or am I
even חייב chayav in the כפל? kefel? Again, maybe not. You know,
maybe to really be a גנב ganav you have to really do
it yourself. But in this issue of the קרן keren is because
of the impact on Michael, and that יש שליח לדבר עבירה, yesh
shliach lidvar aveira, you have you were unwitting, so of course you
were going to do it. Okay, really fascinating משנה, mishna, yes. I'm
sorry, so you know it's a good משנה mishna but it took
a half hour to get through it. Yes. But also might be
the four and five, right? If you paid off as it, four
and five we already learned that טביחה ומכירה tivicha u-mechira you're חייב
על ידי אחר. chayav al yedei acher.
According to רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosfos the חידוש chiddush of this
משנה mishna is that קרן keren you're also חייב על ידי אחר,
chayav al yedei acher, right? The question is are you כפל kefel
you're חייב על ידי אחר. chayav al yedei acher. That's the one
thing we haven't figured out. All right, let's take a look as
the גמרא Gemara continues. בעי רמי בר חמא, Ba'ei Rami bar Chama,
so בעי רמי בר חמא Ba'ei Rami bar Chama asked. תקנו משיכה
בשומרים או לא? Tiknu meshicha be-shomrim o lo? Did they establish משיכה
meshicha for a שומר? shomer? Now what does it mean establish משיכה?
meshicha? Because the general assumption is that הלכתית halachically you only buy
an object when you pay money, but the rabbis said we're not
we're going to get rid of that because Because we want you
to take possession of it. We don't want you to own it
before you take possession of it. It's too confusing, then the guy
has your property, he hasn't given it to you, what happens if
something happens to it? You only own it when you've taken possession
of it, you've done משיכה. meshikha. So משיכה meshikha is a rabbinic
קנין kinyan that overrode the biblical idea of כסף. kesef. So the
question is did we institute a similar קנין kinyan of משיכה meshikha
for שומרים. shomrim. Now presumably that means when is a שומר shomer
חייב hayav for taking the owner's object, for watching it? Only after
the time of משיכה? meshikha? Or what would be the other time?
That's the problem
because by things that there's no money that changed hands, like how
about a מתנה? matana? What would be the biblical act of taking
possession of a gift? Right, when there's no money changed hands, it
can't be the money, so presumably it would be משיכה. meshikha. I
don't know, maybe it would be רשות, reshut, maybe it would be
you have to take it into your property, maybe it would be
הגבהה. hagba'ah. It's not clear what the alternative here is. If for
the שומר shomer there's no alternative of money, but so maybe it's
not clear what the alternative is, but the גמרא's Gemara question is
is משיכה meshikha enough? Maybe you'd have to do הגבהה, hagba'ah, maybe
you'd have to take it into your רשות. reshut. Now רש״י Rashi
says that the question is at what stage is the שומר shomer
חייב hayav if something goes wrong. תוספות Tosafot says no. That was
obvious to the גמרא Gemara that the שומר shomer is only חייב
hayav when he does משיכה. meshikha. Of course, משיכה's meshikha again, it's
fundamentally a transaction that doesn't have money, of course we're going to
institute משיכה meshikha by this, and that's when the שומר shomer becomes
liable. The question is the following: Can the owner change his mind?
Can if I went ahead and I rented you my cow, right,
presumably if you're just a שומר, shomer, then you're totally acting on
my behalf, you're not doing it for your own sake. Although, I
don't know, if you're a שומר שכר shomer sakhar you're trying to
earn money. But let's say I rented you my cow. You only
become liable if something happens once you did משיכה. meshikha. But am
I allowed to back out or not after you've done משיכה? meshikha?
Does משיכה meshikha finalize the deal, not just to make you liable,
but also to prevent me from saying, 'You know what? Forget it,
the rental is off, I want my cow back'? Okay, so that's
how תוספות Tosafot understands it. Does משיכה meshikha prevent the owner from
backing out? So רש״י Rashi says is משיכה meshikha the moment when
you become חייב hayav in liability. Another, let's say I'm your שומר,
shomer, you said, 'Oh can you watch my dog?' 'Yeah, you know,
I'm going to be away, why don't you just, you know, bring
it to my house or something?' Yeah, now רשות reshut would certainly
do it, but the question is take it for granted. Yeah, yeah,
okay. תיקנו משיכה בשומרים או לא. Tiknu meshikha b'shomrim o lo. Okay,
so אמר רב יימר תא שמע, Amar Rav Yeimar Ta shema, come
and hear. נתנו לבכורות בנו. Natanu l'bekhorot beno. Now we're going to
read this of course like we did, that the גנב ganav gave
it to a כהן Cohen for פדיון הבן, pidyon haben, או לבעל
חובו, o l'ba'al khovo, ושומר חינם ושואל נושא שכר ושוכר. v'shomer khinam
v'shoel noseh sakhar v'sokher.
The גנב ganav gave it to any of these people. היה מושכה
ויוצא ומת ברשות הבעלים פטור. Hayah moshkha v'yotze v'met b'reshut haba'alim patur.
So you see that where
we're assuming this שליח לדבר עבירה shaliach l'dvar aveirah idea, but presumably
it only makes sense if the person I gave it to is
doing an act of taking possession. So if משיכה's meshikha just dragging
it, if it's not the act of taking responsibility and the possession,
presumably it would not make me liable. So מאי לאו שומר? mai
lav shomer? You see it means that the שומר shomer is the
one that is taking possession of it through doing the משיכה, meshikha,
and that's why I become a גנב. ganav. But if there was
no act of משיכה meshikha by שומר shomer that was meaningful, it
wouldn't be an act of taking possession, and I wouldn't be חייב
hayav as the גנב. ganav. ושמע מינה תיקנו משיכה בשומרים. U'shma mina
tiknu meshikha b'shomrim. You see that משיכה meshikha makes sense. תוספות Tosafot
says, just to give you the תוספות's Tosafot read, תוספות Tosafot says
it's because if is
that I would only be a גנב ganav if that act of
משיכה meshikha was taking it out of my control. Remember, תוספות's Tosafot
question is after משיכה meshikha am I allowed to back out. So
if after משיכה meshikha I was still allowed to back out, it
wouldn't be an act of גניבה, gneiva, he wouldn't be fully taking
it away from me. It's only if that משיכה meshikha is a
full taking it away from me the גנב, ganav, preventing me from
backing out from the deal, that we say it's like that person
has taken possession of it and he can be my שליח לדבר
עבירה shaliach l'dvar aveirah and I can be a גנב. ganav. Either
way you see that the משיכה meshikha is significant for the שומר.
shomer. שמע מינה תיקנו משיכה בשומרים. Shma mina tiknu meshikha b'shomrim. אמר
ליה לא גנב. Amar lei lo ganav. No, we're not talking that
the שומר shomer was taking it out of the owner's possession, and
the גנב ganav was חייב hayav because of שליח לדבר עבירה. shaliach
l'dvar aveirah. We're now going to read this משנה Mishnah a third
way. That I the גנב ganav gave it to a, excuse me,
no, Michael the owner gave it to a שומר, shomer, or gave
it to a כהן, Cohen, or gave it to whomever, and then
I the גנב ganav was stealing it from the house of the
שומר. shomer. All right, so that's the scenario. So there are three
possible scenarios of the משנה. Mishnah. So confusing, I don't know if
you'll follow if they're נתנו לבכורות בנו. natnu l'bekhorot beno. Okay, so
we have three possibilities.
Here's the owner,
okay, giving it to the... this is the בעל חוב, ba'al hov,
and the owner, or whatever, the כהן. Cohen. etcetera, כהן, Kohen,
שומר, Shomer, okay,
this is the owner. So one possible reading is he gave it
to him. When is that transaction done? Okay, only at the time
of a משיכה. meshicha. That's just talking about the two of them.
That's the one that רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos reject. Okay, so
they read it that it is that the owner gives it to
the, to
a גנב, ganav, okay, here, draw the גנב ganav with like a
dastardly mustache.
I don't know if that's a mustache or what. Okay, anyway, gives
it to the גנב, ganav, okay, and I'm sorry, the owner, no,
no, I'm sorry, he didn't give it to the גנב. ganav. The
גנב, ganav, okay, is the one who gives it to, who gives
it to this guy. Okay. And the question is when does he
become a גנב? ganav? Okay, that's how they read it. When does
he become a גנב? ganav? And it's a question about שליח לדבר
עבירה. shliach lidvar aveira.
לדבר עבירה. lidvar aveira. And the question is when this guy goes
ahead and does this act of משיכה meshicha or הגבהה hagbah or
whatever. And that's the proof of תיקנו משיכה בשומרים. tiknu meshicha b'shomrim.
Oh yeah. That's the proof of תיקנו משיכה בשומרים tiknu meshicha b'shomrim
because obviously if he's a שומר, shomer, if his act is considered
an act of גניבה ganeiva for me because he's an unwittingly מה
שליח, mai-shliach, it's only that same act. The משיכה meshicha has to
be meaningful for him. So that's תיקנו משיכה בשומרים. tiknu meshicha b'shomrim.
And then the גמרא Gemara says, no, no, no. It's a third
scenario. The third scenario of the גמרא Gemara is we're back to
what we said before. Okay. He, the גנב, ganav, but it's the
following. The owner gave it to him, okay, but then היה מושכו
ויוצא, hayo moshcho v'yotzei, you get all three parties involved. Then the
גנב, ganav, this is now נתנו, nasnu, and here is, oops, היה
מושכו. hayo moshcho. Okay, which is, the משנה Mishna reads, the owner
gave it to some third party, a בעל חוב, ba'al chov, a
כהן, Kohen, or שומר, Shomer, and then the גנב ganav was stealing
it from that third party. So if just like the first case
of the משנה, Mishna, the גנב ganav is stealing it from the
owner, now the גנב ganav is stealing it from the third party.
Okay, so that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. There's
no חידוש chidush that way, that's obviously not what we're talking about.
Was it that בעל חוב, ba'al chov, the person who he gave
it to, did sort of קניין? kinyan? Right,
exactly. So in case number one, which we don't read, the owner
is נתנו nasno and this guy is the היה מושכו. hayo moshcho.
He was taking it out and then when does he come from
possession? In scenario number two, okay,
which is now I'm getting confused which is one and which is
two, in scenario number two, hold on, in scenario number two,
my hands are going to be a mess. In scenario number two,
okay, the גנב ganav was נתנו nasno to
to this guy and this guy was still היה מושכו, hayo moshcho,
right? This guy was still the guy taking it away. Either he's
taking it from the owner and then when does that transaction happen
with the owner? Or he's taking it from the גנב ganav and
when does the גנב, ganav, and maybe I'll draw two arrows, right?
And then the גנב, ganav, right, is
נתנו nasno and היה מושכו, hayo moshcho, taking it out of the
property line, right? Got it? This is the red, this is the
blue. Yeah. So he gave it, he took it off of the
property line, when did he become, when did he take possession? He
gave it to this guy, he took it out of the property
line, when was he a גנב ganav through him? Okay. The scenario
number three was, the scenario number three was that the owner was,
here we'll draw it down here. The owner was נתנו nasno to
him,
okay, thank you. The owner was נתנו nasno to him. This this
is scenario see I totally ignored it. Scenario number two is drawn
in blue. Scenario number three is the owner was נתנו nasno to
this בעל חוב, ba'al chov, and the גנב ganav was היה
מושכו, hayo moshcho, the גנב ganav took it away from this guy
and was היה מושכו, hayo moshcho, from his רשות, reshus, from this
guy's רשות. reshus. Alright, that's the case. Alright, let's move on. So
anyway reading it this way it's very boring. It's just another case
of a גנב ganav taking it out of somebody's רשות. reshus. It's
just that the original thing is now in the רשות reshus of
a שומר shomer or of somebody else. Okay, so that's what he
says. Drawing it out, dragging it out like משיכה. meshicha. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says, okay, אמר ליה רב אשי לא תדחייה, Amlei
Rav Ashi lo sidchiyeh,
don't push etcetera, I'm sorry, here's as follows. No, הא har פטור
patur מאי לאו שמע מינה mailav sheshma mina תיקנו משיכה בשומרים? tiknu
meshicha b'shomrim? אמר ליה amlei לא גנב. lo ganav. No, the גנב
ganav is taking it out of the שומר's shomer רשות. reshus. That's
what we're talking about. The גמרא Gemara says one minute, פתני רישא,
patani reisha, the first case was a גנב ganav taking it out
of the owner's רשות. reshus. תני גנב שגנב מבית בעלים, Tanai ganav
sheganav mibeis ba'alim, ותני גנב שגנב מבית השומר. u'tanai ganav sheganav mibeis
hashomeir. Two cases. The גנב ganav stole directly from the owner, or
a גנב ganav stole from the owner who gave it to a
שומר. shomer. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי? mai? What type of
answer is that? מאי גנב שגנב מבית בעלים, mai ganav she-ganav mi-beis
ba'alim, מאי גנב שגנב מבית... mai ganav she-ganav mi-beis...
אמר ליה רב אשי, amar lei Rav Ashi, I'm sorry, אמר ליה
רב אשי, amar lei Rav Ashi, לא תדחיה, lo sitzchi, don't push
him off. מאי גנב שגנב מבית שומר, mai ganav she-ganav mi-beis shomer,
מאי גנב שגנב מבית בעלים. mai ganav she-ganav mi-beis ba'alim. That's crazy.
You wouldn't give a whole second case of the משנה Mishna to
say, oh, the owner gave it to a שומר shomer and then
the exact same story with the גנב ganav taking it now from
the שומר. shomer. So אלא לאו ela lav שומר, shomer, it is
talking about the שומר shomer was taking it out at the behest
of the גנב ganav without, while being unwitting, and therefore the act
of משיכה meshicha of the שומר shomer is a meaningful act.
ושמע מינה תיקנו משיכה בשומרים שמע מינה. u-shema mina tiknu meshicha be-shomrim
shema mina. You see משיכה meshicha is a meaningful act for a
שומר. shomer. That's a good proof. איתמר נמי, itmar nami, it was
also taught. אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabi Elazar, כשם שתיקנו משיכה בלקוחות,
kesheim she-tiknu meshicha be-lokuchoos, the same way משיכה meshicha takes possession of
an object, כך תיקנו משיכה בשומרים. kach tiknu meshicha be-shomrim. That's also
when a שומר, shomer, either according to רש"י Rashi becomes liable, or
according to תוספות Tosafos when the owner cannot back out. תניא נמי
הכי, tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly,
כשם שתיקנו משיכה בלקוחות כך תיקנו משיכה בשומרים. kesheim she-tiknu meshicha be-lokuchoos
kach tiknu meshicha be-shomrim. וכשם, u-kesheim, one more line to this ברייתא,
Baraisa, שהקרקע נקנית בכסף שטר וחזקה, she-ha-karka nikneis be-kesef shtar va-chazaka, the
same way land is purchased with כסף, kesef, שטר, shtar, and חזקה,
chazaka, money, a document, and a physical taking possession, כך שכירות נקנית
בכסף שטר וחזקה. kach schirus nikneis be-kesef shtar va-chazaka. Rentals take place
through money, a document, or חזקה. chazaka. So the גמרא Gemara says
שכירות דמאי, schirus de-mai, rentals of what? אילימא שכירות דמטלטלין, eileima schirus
de-mitaltelin, if it's rentals of chattels, okay, like I'm going to borrow
your car, rent your car, מטלטלין בני שטר נינהו? mitaltelin benei shtar
ninhu? So there could be כסף kesef by cattle and maybe they
allowed it to work here, but you don't write a document on
cattle? Why not? Like I sign a rental agreement for your car.
Yeah, well, that's we do, but in הלכה Halacha you don't. הלכה,
Halacha, documents are never seen as meaningful because, you know, you can
never identify a particular object. I mean, nowadays we got VIN numbers
on cars. But anyway, but you know, documents are only meaningful about
land or עבדים, avadim, slaves. So therefore, obviously we're not talking about
cattle. So אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Chisda, שכירות דקרקע. schirus de-karka.
No, no, when you're like renting a house or you're renting an
apartment, then you take possession the same way, you know, you take
possession of it if you were buying it. Okay, אמר רבי אלעזר,
amar Rabi Elazar,
ועתה, ve-ata, now we get to, because we talked about this fascinating
thing of the מעשה קנין ma'aseh kinyan of a גנב, ganav, now
we're going to get to a great גמרא Gemara to talk about
the question of the identity of a גנב ganav and the line
between a גנב ganav and a גזלן. gazlan. אמר רבי אלעזר, amar
Rabi Elazar, ראהו שהטמין בחורשין. ra'ahu she-hitmin be-chorshin. You saw a guy
hiding in the forest and he was basically hiding to capture, you
know, sheep that wandered by. Okay, you know, so he was and
וטבח ומכר, ve-tavach u-machar, and he slaughtered and sold, משלם תשלומי ארבעה
וחמישה, meshaleim tashlumei arba'ah va-chamisha, you pay four and five. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says אמאי הלא משך? amai halo mashach? Maybe they're
out of the owner's רשות, reshus, now, you know, but he didn't
do a משיכה. meshicha. He just captured it in the forest and
he slaughtered it right there. He didn't do a הגבהה, hagbaha, he
didn't do a משיכה. meshicha. אמר רב חסדא שהקישו במקל. amar Rav
Chisda she-hikisho be-makel. He did do a משיכה. meshicha. He saw the
sheep and he hit it and made it follow him. So then
what's the big חידוש? chiddush? But before we get to that, you
know, you always should stop and wonder and ask. Yeah, or the
forest could be הפקר. hefker. Okay, you know, the forest if it's
not, if it's not the person's particular רשות. reshus. But you always
should wonder, like, if the גמרא, Gemara, when it reinterprets it, is
it possible that it's actually reinterpreting it away from its original meaning?
Because if you think about it, this statement might actually be reflecting
a פשט pshat read of the משנה. Mishna. The משנה Mishna says
גנב חוץ מרשותם, ganav chutz me-reshusam, right? The end of the משנה
Mishna said if I'm taking it out of their רשות, reshus, if
it starts in their property, I have to do a משיכה meshicha
or a הגבהה. hagbaha. Let's say it started out of their property.
Let's say I found it wandering in a forest. Maybe I don't
have to do a משיכה, meshicha, right? Now, of course, exactly what
moment I become a גנב ganav I don't know, but that's a
literal reading of the משנה Mishna of גנב חוץ מרשותם, ganav chutz
me-reshusam, right? But anyway, the גמרא Gemara rejects that. The גמרא Gemara
says no, no, no, he did a משיכה. meshicha. אמר רב חסדא
שהקישו במקל. amar Rav Chisda she-hikisho be-makel. אמאי, amai, so the גמרא
Gemara says, okay fine, וכיון דראוהו, ve-keivan de-ra'uhu, I don't get it.
If you're seeing him, גזלן הוא, gazlan hu, he's not a גנב.
ganav. A גנב ganav is somebody who does it in hiding. Now
רש"י Rashi says I don't understand. רש"י Rashi says we just got
through all these משניות Mishnayos about witnesses seeing somebody being a גנב.
ganav. Why don't you say every time witnesses saw him, he stops
being a גנב? ganav? You'd never have to pay four and five.
Oh, there are witnesses, I did it, I'm not a גנב. ganav.
So רש"י Rashi says so the basic answer is no, no, there
you did it thinking nobody would see you, but two people happened
to see you. Here the point is, at least what the גמרא
Gemara assumes, is that a forest is a public space. Anybody can
walk in and see you there. Okay? So you are still a,
so why aren't you a גזלן? gazlan? You're doing it in a
way in which you are, it's, your actions are easily visible to
the public. Okay? So the
גמרא Gemara says כיון דקמטמרי מינייהו גנב הוא. keivan de-ka-mitmari mineihu ganav
hu. It's true he is, like somebody could see him, but nevertheless
he is hiding out. Now, you know, it could be as we're
going to see in a minute that the reason he's hiding out
is because he wants the sheep to wander by and he doesn't
want people to avoid him. It's not because he's afraid of people.
But nevertheless it's saying like there's a, it's true, it's not like
totally like the גנב ganav who breaks into your house in the
middle of the night and nobody knows whatever, you know, here it
is part. Possible to see see a guy in a forest hiding
out if you walk by him you'll see him there, but nevertheless
there is an element of trying to be, you know, trying not
to do it out and out in the open. Okay. So how
does he do it in broad daylight? Well, that's that's going to
be the גמרא's Gemara question. What's the שיעור shiur of being a
גזלן? gazlan? So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says
ואלא גזלן היכי דמי? v'ela gazlan heichi dami? So then what's a
גזלן? gazlan? If that's a גנב, ganav, what's a גזלן? gazlan? And
also, you know, so the other point by the way is that
a classic גנב ganav like if you look up in in the
legal definition of burglary, it's breaking into the owner's property. It's like
breaking in in secret to the owner's property, right? Whereas a גזלן
gazlan you imagine somebody accosting you in the middle of the street,
like you know, a mugging or something. Okay, so here you're not
breaking into somebody's property. You get the the thing wanders by your
way, right? So therefore that sounds like a גזלן, gazlan, you know,
you bump into somebody on the street and you stick a gun
in their face. The sheep walks up. So here you could be
a גנב ganav without ever entering the owner's property. Right. Like he
was bumping and hiding are two I mean he was like pre-meditated.
I understand it was pre-meditated but it wasn't an entering into the
owner's property, right? So that's number one a big חידוש, chiddush, right?
It's not entering into the owner's property, it's not totally in hiding,
it's possible to be seen, and even so you're a גנב. ganav.
So who's a גזלן? gazlan? What's the punishment for a גזלן gazlan
then? Just קרן. keren. Yeah. ממילא. me'mela. Exactly. I don't know why
everybody doesn't go into the business of being a גזלן gazlan because
the worst thing is you pay the money back. Okay so anyway
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. The גמרא Gemara says now
כיון דמטמרי מיטמרי ואלא גזלן היכי דמי? keivan de-mitmorei mityamrei v'ela gazlan
heichi dami? What's a גזלן? gazlan? אמר רבי אבהו amar Rabbi Abahu
כגון בניהו בן יהוידע. kegon Benayahu ben Yehoyada. Oh,
like בניהו בן יהוידע Benayahu ben Yehoyada he did when he met
up with this this מצרי. Mitzri. שנאמר ויגזל את החנית מיד המצרי
ויהרגהו בחניתו. she-ne'emar vayigzol et hachanit miyad hamitzri vayihar-gehu bechanito.
He accosted the guy straight in the front street in public and
he took his, you know, his spear or whatever and he you
know killed him with his spear. Okay. רבי יוחנן אמר Rabbi Yochanan
amar כגון- kegon like
I got to tell you guys, I don't- I can't read this
גמרא Gemara without thinking about many years ago, it must have been
like 20 years ago or whatever, I was like mugged when I
was, thank God, I mean I was, you know, not hurt or
anything. But it was like broad daylight. It was on Broadway and
like 93rd street, I still remember it. And yeah, just somebody comes
up to me, you know, sometimes they come and they ask you
for like money as a way to get close or something like
that, and just pushes me into like this little niche in a
store, you know like a like an open like how a store
like, you know, you know indents in like for there to be
a door and an opening and people like walking by, you know,
but they, you know, "give us your money, give us your money"
whatever. I mean I only had like ten dollars, I'm glad actually
it's not a good thing. I'm glad that they didn't hurt me,
you know sometimes they don't have enough money. But it's like it
was broad daylight, there were people around, like why wasn't anybody doing
anything? Anyway, then afterwards some people consoled me. But anyway, so that
would be a
גזלן. gazlan. Okay. Okay. רבי יוחנן אמר כגון בעלי שכם. Rabbi Yochanan
amar kegon ba'alei Shechem. Like the people of שכם. Shechem. שנאמר וישימו
לו בעלי שכם מארבים. she-ne'emar vayasimu lo ba'alei Shechem ma'arvim. They created
like these- what are they called? The people that like- liars- if
they lied in wait, you know an ambush. על ראשי ההרים al
rashei heharim by the tops of the mountains ויגזלו את כל אשר
יעבר עליהם בדרך. vayigzolu et kol asher ya'avor aleihem baderech. Anybody that
passed through the way, you know below, they would ambush them from
above. What? sounds like the גמרא's Gemara going to ask they're hiding.
So let's take a look. Okay. רבי אבהו מאי טעמא לא אמר
מהאי? Rabbi Abahu mai ta'ama lo amar me'hai? So why didn't he
tell you from from that פסוק pasuk about the ambush? אמר לך
כיון דמטמרי אטמורי. amar lach keivan demitmorei itmurei. No,
cause they're hiding. לאו גזלנין נינהו. lav gazlanin ninhu. They're not
blatant enough. They're not גזלן. gazlan. They're hiding. רבי יוחנן- Rabbi Yochanan
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said no, הא דקמטמרי דלא לחיזיונהו אינש וליערקו
מנייהו. ha de-kamitmorei delo lachzeinhu inish v'li'arku minaihu. Why are they hiding?
So that the victims should not avoid them. They're not hiding because
they're afraid of people. They're willing to do the act out in
the open. It's just a matter- yeah that's right. They just want-
don't want people to avoid them. Right. So according to רבי יוחנן-
Rabbi Yochanan so one is anybody that hides at all that's not,
you know, completely whatever is not a גנב ganav and רבי יוחנן's
Rabbi Yochanan a little more reasonable. No, no, no, if you're hiding
just to, you know, just so that you can ambush somebody that's
fine. But if you're but the key is- not fine, whatever. That
you know then you're still a- then you're then you're still a
גזלן. gazlan. A גנב ganav though has to a- hide and b-
hide because he's afraid to be caught, not because he's afraid that
people will avoid him. He's afraid to be caught. Okay so everybody
sort of certainly agrees that a גזלן gazlan has to be somebody
who's prepared to do his act out in the open and not
afraid to be seen or caught in the perpetration of his act.
Okay that's sort of agreed upon. All right. So now why should
that be the definition? and which gets to the heart of why
does a גנב ganav pay- why does a גנב ganav pay more
than a גזלן? gazlan? Right? If the- so this is actually what
the גמרא's Gemara actually going to get to. We get a little
bit of like a little טעמא דקרא ta'ama dekra here. So let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
שאלו תלמידיו את רבי יוחנן בן זכאי. sha'alu talmidav et Rabbi Yochanan
ben Zakkai. The students asked רבי יוחנן בן זכאי Rabbi Yochanan ben
Zakkai מפני מה החמירה תורה בגנב יותר מבגזלן? mipnei mah hechmirah Torah
beganav yoter mibigazlan? Why is the Torah stricter for a גנב ganav
than a גזלן gazlan to make him pay כפל kefel or even
four and five? אמר להן- amar lahen he said to them זה
השוה כבוד עבד לכבוד קונו. zeh hishveh kevod eved likvod kono. Because
the גזלן gazlan treated the servants like the Master. Treated people like
God. He's not afraid of any of them. At least he's not
hiding. hypocrisy there, he's willing to do it all in the open.
וזה, Vezeh, and the גנב ganav לא השווה כבוד עבד לכבוד קונו,
lo hishva kevod eved likhvod kono, does not equate the servant with
the Master. It really means the master with the servant, this is
all said in the reverse as a sort of לשון, lashon, you
know, because it's a euphemism, but does not treat God as well
as he treats the human being. כביכול, Kiviyachol, he made עין של
מטה ayin shel mata means עין של מעלה. ayin shel ma'ala. Okay,
it's sort of said in the reverse. It makes it as if...
right, exactly. It makes it as if the heavenly eye, כאילו אינו
רואה, ke'ilu eino ro'eh, isn't seeing. And the אוזן של מטה ozen
shel mata as if the heavenly ear, כאילו אינו שומע, ke'ilu eino
shome'a, isn't hearing. You're afraid of people, your acts you're not willing
to do out in the open, but from God, you're not afraid.
Now, could be that you're not afraid like you're ashamed of people,
you just don't want to get caught. Right. Okay, but nevertheless, but
that explains why somebody could go ahead and do an act that's
out and out an open act of theft, but because you go
ahead and like you hide afterwards and you don't want to get
caught, you're halachically defined as a גנב ganav because that is making
you a... that shows that you're afraid of, you know, you're afraid
of people. Okay, so it actually broadens the definition of גנב. ganav.
גנב Ganav becomes a very broad definition. Anything you do that shows
that you're hiding because you're afraid to get caught or afraid of
people seeing you or whatever, even if the act itself is a
sort of a very, you know, blatant act, makes you a גנב.
ganav. So if at any point I hide? Well, here the גמרא
Gemara is talking about before or during, but the גמרא, Gemara, the
reason I said later is because if you might remember, there's a
גמרא Gemara about ליסטיס מזוין listis mezuyan that actually said according to
one opinion that that was a גנב, ganav, even armed robbers if
they hide afterwards. So I should have said that explicitly. If you
might remember, that was an earlier discussion. So there's even a possibility
even if the whole thing was out in the open, if some
part of the process there's a hiding and a showing that you're
afraid of people, that makes you the, you know, the hypocrite גנב
ganav and you get the weightier punishment. Okay. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as the
verse says: הוי המעמיקים מה', Hoy hama'amikim meHashem,
those that sort of, you know, hide things from God, לסתיר עצה,
lastir eitzah,
to hide their plans, והיה במחשך מעשיהם, vehayah bemachshach ma'aseihem, and they
do their deeds in the... you know, in darkness. וכתיב, Uchtiv, and
it says: ויאמרו לא יראה יה, vayamru lo yireh Yah, God does
not see, ולא יבין אלוהי יעקב, velo yavin elohei Yaakov, the God
of Jacob does not understand. וכתיב: Uchtiv: כי אמרו עזב ה' את
הארץ ואין ה' רואה, ki amru azav Hashem et ha'aretz ve'ein Hashem
ro'eh, God does not see. So there's a whole act of fundamental,
like, theological, you know,
heresy going on here. It's not just hypocrisy, it's you're... yeah, because
hypocrisy is the wrong way of saying it. That's just saying you're
inconsistent. It's more like heresy, it's more showing like you don't care
about God. It's theologically, you know, profoundly offensive. The four and five
is like the פסקא, piska, he kept going with it, God's completely
not watching. Maybe. Right. I don't know if you read the four
and five consistent with that or consistent just with what you're, you
know, increasing in terms of taking it away from the owner. Because
the four and five could be out in the public, you know,
but yeah, it's an interesting point whether we read the four and
five in the same way. Okay, let's finish to the משנה. mishnah.
אמר רבי מאיר: Amar Rabbi Meir: משל משלו רבן גמליאל למה הדבר
דומה, mashal mashlu Rabban Gamliel lemah hadavar domeh,
what's it like? לשני בני אדם שהיו בעיר, Lishnei benei adam shehayu
be'ir, two people in a village, ועשו משתה, ve'asu mishteh, they made
a feast. אחד זימן את בני העיר ולא זימן את בני המלך,
Echad ziman et benei ha'ir velo ziman et benei hamelech, one invited
all the people of the village but not the family of the
king. ואחד לא זימן את בני העיר ולא זימן את בני המלך.
Ve'echad lo ziman et benei ha'ir velo ziman et benei hamelech. The
other one didn't do it... you know, just for family we're keeping
it small, they didn't invite the villagers and they didn't invite the
princes, the בני המלך. benei hamelech. איזה מהן עונשו
מרובה, Eizeh mehen onsho merubeh, who did a worse thing? הוי אומר:
Havei omer: זה שזימן את בני העיר ולא זימן את בני המלך,
zeh sheziman et benei ha'ir velo ziman et benei hamelech, the one
who made it, you know, was willing to give the honor to
the villagers but not to the sons of the king. So if
you would say, I don't understand, a גזלן gazlan is worse, he
doesn't care about God and he doesn't care about people. אה, Ah,
but at least he's not showing he cares more about people than
God. You don't care about anyone! Right! The גנב ganav is worse.
The גנב ganav is the one that cares about people and doesn't
care about God. אמר רבי מאיר: Amar Rabbi Meir: בוא וראה כמה
גדול כוח של מלאכה. Bo ure'eh kamah gadol koach shel melachah. Now
that we're talking about the reasons behind it, let's point about the
four and the five. Come and see the value of labor.
שור שביטלו ממלאכתו, Shor shebitlo mimalachto, when you steal an ox, what's
the impact of stealing an ox? You're taking away somebody's, like, form
of livelihood. You're taking away their tractor, you know, and their milk
producer. So in that case, חמישה, chamishah, you have to pay five
times. This is why the תורה Torah makes... that's probably פשט pshat
I assume, I think why the תורה Torah says you pay more
by the ox than the sheep because this is the staples of
a person's livelihood and why an ox more than a sheep? Because
a sheep is about slaughtering it and its wool and its whatever,
an ox is about working the land.
I understand that, but it's so... so you took, but that's like
stealing. So you took away something of value, but here you took
away something that was continuing to actually work the land and had
much bigger, right, you took away the means of production. Okay, so
that's five.
שה שלא ביטלו ממלאכתו, Seh shelo bitlo mimalachto, שה seh you stopped
it from, you know, being a thing of value but you didn't
stop it from like all this production. So in that case, ארבעה,
arba'ah, only four. So that to me is the better explanation. The
next one is the one I think רש''י Rashi quotes on חומש.
Chumash. and everybody gets taught in grade school. אמר רבן יוחנן בן
זכאי *Amar Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai* בוא וראה כמה גדול *Bo ure-ei
kama gadol* which is consistent with our previous idea כמה גדול כבוד
הבריות *kama gadol kevod habriyos* no no no the dignity of people
שור שהלך ברגליו *Shor shehalach beraglav* when you stole the ox you
were able to walk it out so there you you weren't embarrassing
yourself so the fine is going to be heavy חמישה *chamishah* שה
שכיב על כתפו *seh shehikiv al ktefo* the the sheep that you
had to put on your on your shoulders and run out with
that was your embarrassment so because you embarrassed yourself a little bit
the Torah goes a little easier on you and says ארבע *arba*.
Okay we will end with this.